<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE PMSC-UGR-ARTICLE SYSTEM "PMSC-UGR-ARTICLE.dtd">
<PMSC-UGR-ARTICLE>
  <PUBLICATED-IN>European heart journal</PUBLICATED-IN>
  <DOCUMENT-TYPE>ARTICLE</DOCUMENT-TYPE>
  <PUBLICATION-ISSN>0195-668X</PUBLICATION-ISSN>
  <ARTICLE-PMID>16299020</ARTICLE-PMID>
  <ARTICLE-TITLE>N-terminal brain natriuretic peptide as a screening tool for heart failure in the pacemaker population.</ARTICLE-TITLE>
  <ARTICLE-INFO>4, 27, 447-53</ARTICLE-INFO>
  <ARTICLE-DATE>
    <ARTICLE-DAY>NSA</ARTICLE-DAY>
    <ARTICLE-MONTH>Feb</ARTICLE-MONTH>
    <ARTICLE-YEAR>2006</ARTICLE-YEAR>
  </ARTICLE-DATE>
  <ARTICLE-ABSTRACT>Assessment of N-terminal brain natriuretic peptide (NT-BNP) as a screening tool for heart failure in patients with a permanent pacemaker.Consecutive patients undergoing a routine permanent pacemaker assessment were enrolled. Patients underwent medical history and examination, echocardiography and blood sampling for NT-BNP. Analysis was performed on 261 patients (132 DDD, 121 VVI, eight others), mean age 73+/-12 years, range 34-99 years. Seventy two subjects (27%) had heart failure as defined by left ventricular ejection fraction (LVEF) &lt;or=40% and symptoms of heart failure (NYHA class II, III, or IV). Screening with NT-BNP gave a sensitivity of 73% and specificity of 72% for detecting heart failure in all patients [area under the curve (AUC) 0.76, P&lt;0.001, 95% CI 0.69-0.83]. This increased in subjects with a DDD type pacemaker (sensitivity 80%, specificity 66%, AUC=0.8, CI 0.7-0.90) and reduced in subjects with a VVI type pacemaker (sensitivity 66%, specificity 61%, AUC 0.68 CI 0.57-0.78).Symptoms of heart failure are common in patients with pacemakers. Screening with NT-BNP is feasible and assists in the detection of important cardiac co-morbidity, particularly in patients with a DDD type pacemaker.</ARTICLE-ABSTRACT>
  <ARTICLE-SUBJECTS>Adult D000328, Aged D000368, Aged, 80 and over D000369, Biomarkers D015415, blood D015415, Cardiac Pacing, Artificial D002304, Echocardiography D004452, False Positive Reactions D005189, Heart Failure D006333, diagnosis D006333, Humans D006801, Middle Aged D008875, Mitral Valve Insufficiency D008944, diagnosis D008944, Natriuretic Peptide, Brain D020097, blood D020097, Peptide Fragments D010446, blood D010446, ROC Curve D012372, Risk Factors D012307</ARTICLE-SUBJECTS>
  <ARTICLE-KEYWORDS />
  <ARTICLE-AUTHORS>john gf cleland (0000-0002-1471-7016), k m goode (0000-0003-1963-345X)</ARTICLE-AUTHORS>
  <ARTICLE-AUTHORS-ORCIDS>
    <ORCID>0000-0002-1471-7016</ORCID>
    <ORCID>0000-0003-1963-345X</ORCID>
  </ARTICLE-AUTHORS-ORCIDS>
  <CITATIONS />
  <REFERENCES>
    <REFERENCE>
      <REFERENCE-PMID>7702044</REFERENCE-PMID>
      <REFERENCE-AUTHORS-ORCIDS>0000-0001-5879-6193</REFERENCE-AUTHORS-ORCIDS>
    </REFERENCE>
    <REFERENCE>
      <REFERENCE-PMID>8309035</REFERENCE-PMID>
      <REFERENCE-AUTHORS-ORCIDS>0000-0002-1453-3196</REFERENCE-AUTHORS-ORCIDS>
    </REFERENCE>
  </REFERENCES>
</PMSC-UGR-ARTICLE>
